Finding Aid for Detroit Ophthalmological Club records, 1902-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Detroit Ophthalmological Club records 1902-2011 1915-2011
Detroit Ophthalmological Club.
1.5 linear feet and 1 volume
95105 Bn 2
Professional-social club for Detroit area ophthalmologists. Correspondence, constitution and bylaws, minutes of meetings, history of the organization, and a case report detailing the early use of X-ray photography for ophthalmological procedures performed in Eloise, Michigan, in 1897.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group has been donated by the Detroit Ophthalmological Club (donor number 8436 ) and came to the library through Dr. T. G. Varbedian, November 1995. Additional records have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The Detroit Ophthalmological Club (hereafter D.O.C.) was established as the Detroit Ophthalmological and Otological Club. A brief history, written by Dr. L.C. Maire, long-term member of the club, estimated the approximate founding year for the organization as 1902. The club was the successor organization to the Wayne County Medical Society Section for Diseases of the Eye, Ear, Nose and Throat. Its purpose was "to fill a long felt want to those who were directing their attention exclusively to the two specialties, ophthalmology and otology." The D.O.C. was formed to provide a social setting for presenting papers, and exchanging information in the developing science of ophthalmology. The club's name was shortened to Detroit Ophthalmological Club in 1928.
From its beginnings, membership in the club has been limited to 30 members. Prospective candidates for membership are still voted into the club by current members. The club comprises ophthalmologists residing in Detroit, its suburbs, Ann Arbor, and the University of Michigan.
The records of the organization include correspondence, a copy of the club's constitution and bylaws, with revisions, and brief minutes of meetings. Also included with the records are a brief history and a case report detailing the early use of X-ray photography for ophthalmological procedures performed in Eloise, Michigan in 1897. The record group also includes the record book, 1902-1904, for D.O.C.'s predecessor organization, the Wayne County Medical Society Section for Diseases of the Eye, Ear, Nose, and Throat. The record book contains minutes, bylaws, and lists of members.
Subjects:
Detroit Ophthalmological Club.; Ophthalmology--Michigan.; Ophthalmic photography.; Eloise (Hospital: Wayne County, Mich.)
- Organizational records
  - A Brief History of Detroit Ophthalmological Club (Box 1)
  - Constitution and bylaws of D.O.C. (April 1935 revision) (Box 1)
  - Case Report on Early Use of X-Ray Photography, Eloise, Michigan, 1897 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1919 and 1928 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1979 including copy of bylaw revisions, April 30, 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1996 and 2005-2011, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1915-2002, 5 notebooks, 1 folder, and 1 expandable folder (Box 2)
  - Member Obituaries, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Record book, 1902-1904 of the Wayne County Medical Society section for Diseases of he Eye, Ear, Nose and Throat (Box 2)
    (The section was a predecessor of the Detroit Ophthalmological and Otolaryngological Club.)
  - Photo album of centennial celebration, 2004 (Volume 1)